Aaron Apple

(847) 970-0924 • apple@cogsci.jhu.edu • aaronapple.github.io/

Profile

Recent graduate of the Department of Cognitive Science at Johns Hopkins University with a background in language processing and visual perception research and expertise in quantitative analysis and data visualization. Experienced in leading and managing research, with excellent interpersonal skills, intellectual curiosity, and a rigorous approach to solving complex problems.

Education

Johns Hopkins University

Baltimore, MD

Masters of Arts in Cognitive Science

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

Advisors: Drs. Akira Omaki, Kyle Rawlins & Geraldine Legendre

Linguistics Society of America

Chicago, IL

New York, NY

Graduate of the 2015 LSA Summer Institute at the University of Chicago

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

New York University
Bachelors of Arts in Language and Mind, Minor in Creative Writing

Aug. 2008 - Dec. 2012

Skills

Research: Experimental design; Quantitative analysis; Data visualization; Scientific writing; Public speaking;

Data management; Research coordination; Grant editing; Eye tracking; Corpus linguistics

Programming: R (advanced); Python (proficient); MATLAB (proficient); HTML (familiar); JavaScript (familiar)

Graphic Design: Vector illustration (Adobe Illustrator); Vector animation (Anime Studio Pro)

Software: Google Docs & Sheets; Microsoft Office Suite; Adobe Creative Cloud; FileMaker Pro; Audacity;

Ableton Live; SR Research Experiment Builder & Data Viewer

Statistical Methods: ANOVA; Mixed-effects regression; Bayesian inference; Neural networks

Languages: English (native); French (proficient)

Professional Experience

Manager of the Language Processing and Development Lab

Baltimore, MD

PI: Dr. Akira Omaki, Department of Cognitive Science, The Johns Hopkins University

Jan. 2013 - Jul. 2015

- o Team leader and designer for 2 experiments on child and adult linguistic and visual processing.
- o Developed and maintained pipelines to manage, analyze, and visualize data for 12 experiments.
- Supervised 5 research assistants on 4 research projects.
- Designed visual and linguistic stimuli for 6 experiments.
- $\circ~$ Wrote 5 articles submitted to peer-reviewed journals and presented findings at 2 conferences.
- Conducted literature reviews for 7 experiments.
- Managed 3 IRB protocols.
- Edited NSF grant application for a project on child sentence processing and executive control.
- o Wrote, designed, and edited newsletter presenting findings from 8 experiments for laypeople.

Research Assistant in the Davachi Memory Lab

New York, NY

May 2012 - *Dec.* 2012

PI: Dr. Lila Davachi, Department of Psychology, New York University

Assisted in designing and coding MEG experiment on memory reactivation.

7 Assisted in designing and coding type experiment on memory reactivation.

• Managed participant recruitment and data collection for 2 fMRI experiments.

Research Assistant in the Consciousness and Computation Lab

PI: Dr. Hakwan Lau, Department of Psychology, Columbia University

New York, NY *May* 2012 - Dec. 2012

• Designed and coded behavioral experiment on dynamic control of memory and attention.

• Managed participant recruitment and data collection for 3 behavioral experiments.

Research Assistant in the Neurolinguistics Lab

PI: Dr. Liina Pylkkänen, Department of Linguistics, New York University

• Designed and coded MEG experiment on domain generality of semantic processing.

Editorial Intern at DVL Seigenthaler Public Relations Agency

• Wrote 12 press releases for 3 business clients.

• Copy edited press releases and outreach magazines for 2 philanthropic clients.

Intern at 826CHI

• Administered the after-school tutoring program of 30 children and tutors.

o Taught writing as a teaching assistant in 2 English classes in a Chicago public high school.

Research Assistant for Syntactic Structures of The Worlds Languages

PI: Dr. Chris Collins, Department of Linguistics, New York University

• Developed program to visualize syntactic and phylogenetic relationships between languages.

New York, NY

Sept. 2011 - April 2012

Chicago, IL

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

Chicago, IL

New York, NY

Jan. 2009 - June 2009

Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

Publications, Presentations and Awards

Atkinson, E., Apple, A., Omaki, A. (2016). Similarity of Wh-Phrases and Acceptability Variation in Wh-Islands. *Frontiers in Psychology*, 6.

Omaki, A, Lau, E. F., Davidson White, I., Dakan, M., Apple, A., & Phillips, C. (2015). Hyper-active gap filling. Frontiers in Psychology, 6.

Apple, A. & Omaki, A. (2015). Incrementality and garden-path recovery in children's resolution of direct object vs. sentential complement ambiguity. Paper presented at the Boston University Conference on Language Development, November 13, 2015.

Apple, A. & Omaki, A. (2015). Development of sentential complement ambiguity processing. Poster presented at the CUNY 2015 Conference on Sentence Processing, March 21.

Omaki, A. & Apple, A. (2014). Adaptation of active gap filling in coordinated sentences. Talk presented at the AMLaP 2014, September 4.

Apple, A., Bemis, D., Marcus, G., Pylkkänen, L. (2012). Domain General Compositional Processing: An MEG Study. Dean's Undergraduate Research Fund, NYU. Poster presented at the Dean's Undergraduate Research conference and grant recipient of the highest award, \$1000.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). The role of incremental parsing on Japanese infants' word learning.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Japanese infants' abstract knowledge of word order.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Filler-gap processing in coordinate structures.

Apple, A., Omaki, A. (In preparation). Incrementality and garden-path recovery in child resolution of complement ambiguity.

Volunteering

Harwood Community Association

Baltimore, MD

Volunteer and organizer

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2016

- o Harwood's 2016 National Night Out Against Crime: Solicited food donations from local businesses, ran the BBQ grill, and assisted in managing other volunteers.
- o The 2015 Ilchester Back to School Block Party: Solicited school supplies donations from local businesses and assisted in managing other volunteers.